Finding Aid for Peter A. Ostafin Papers, 1939-1982.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Peter A. Ostafin Papers 1939-1982, 1955-1975
Ostafin, Peter A.
5 linear feet
861124 Aa 2
Assistant director of men and director of housing at the University of Michigan. Collected materials largely relating to student housing at the University of Michigan; also files on student activities, including problems of transportation.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the Housing Office of the University of Michigan in June 1984 (Donor No. 5013 ).
The collection is open to research.
Ostafin was active at the University of Michigan for twenty years from the mid-1950s to the mid-1970s. He served in many capacities, including Assistant to the Vice-President of Student Community Relations, Assistant to the Director of Housing, and Assistant Director of Men. He was a member of a wide variety of committees and commissions, such as the Joint Committee on Central Business District Hi-Rise Developments and Parking (1964), the University Safety Committee (1964), the Parking Operations Committee (1968-1971), the Commission on Student Governance (1973-1975), and other groups. Ostafin was involved in student housing, both on-campus and off-campus, especially during the upheavals of the 1960s, when racial discrimination in housing, co-ed housing, and the development of North Campus were prominent issues. He was also interested in students' lives outside the dormitories and campus, ranging from the problems of vandalism and crime to community volunteer programs.
The Peter A. Ostafin Papers consist of both personal and official (University of Michigan) records that reflect his professional career in housing at the University of Michigan from 1955 to 1977. The records cover a range of subjects that include housing developments at the university, transportation issues, student governance, a variety of student activities, and administrative activities and issues. Materials found include minutes, reports, proposals, memoranda, newspaper clippings, and a variety of background and source documents relating to housing, transportation, and student affairs. The original order of the collection consisted of topical folders and loose documents in a random order. Scattered throughout the collection are documents created by and for both John Feldkamp, director of Housing, and Barbara Newell, vice-president for Student Affairs. Outside the strengths of the collection, much of the remaining material is scattered throughout the topical files and is of limited importance. Included are materials that mostly serve to illustrate sources consulted by the various groups on which Ostafin served. These reference materials form the majority of the early records, some dating back to the early 1940s.
Although the papers touch on many aspects of both students' lives and housing, the strength of the collection lies particularly in several specific areas: Housing (including both University and non-University), Student Activities, Transportation, and the Southeast Michigan Council of Governments.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; University of Michigan. Office of Student Affairs.; University of Michigan. Office of Student Community Relations.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.
- Housing
  Within the Housing series are materials that document Ostafin's involvement with health issues in the university housing system, the residence halls (especially the governing body of the halls), cooperative housing (the Inter-Cooperative Council or ICC), and racial discrimination in both on- and off-campus housing. The health reports, from the late 1950s and early 1960s, touch on all subjects of health, from cases of food poisoning in the dormitory cafeterias to the poor condition of some of the affiliated houses (i.e. fraternity and sorority houses). Records of the "Board of Governors of Residence Halls" document, in part, the issues faced by the halls on an everyday basis and in larger contexts, such as racial integration in the dormitories rooms. The question of racism is continued in the off-campus housing files which deal with this issue outside of the protective environment of the residence halls.
  The "Cooperative Housing" files, while not complete by any means, offer insight into the Inter-Cooperative Council during the sixties and early seventies. Because the option of cooperative housing was first offered in a college setting at the University of Michigan beginning in the 1930s, these files are noteworthy despite their limitations. The strengths of the records lie in the documentation of the ICC's acquisition of North Campus property and the details of applications to the Department of Housing and Urban Development for grants to build and improve its houses. For the scholar of cooperative living on the student level, the University of Michigan should be one of the premier places for study. The researcher should also consult the records of the Inter-cooperative Council of the University of Michigan.
  Also documented in the Housing series is the entire lifespan of the "Joint Committee on Central Business District Hi-Rise Development and Parking." Meeting minutes, the report, and a rebuttal of the report are present in the Joint Committee files. Also a variety of housing projects, especially the development of Oxford Housing in the early 1960s and several North Campus projects, are documented in this series.
  - General Materials
    - General 1960-1969 (Box 1)
    - Calendar Study Committee 1958-1977 (Box 1)
    - Campus Planning 1956-1974 (Box 1)
    - Campus Security 1947-1970 (Box 1)
    - College Housing Loan Program 1957-1967 (Box 1)
    - Continuing Enrollment Deposit 1962-1964
      - Correspondence 1962-1964 (Box 1)
      - Meeting Minutes 1962-1964 (Box 1)
      - Procedures 1962-1964 (Box 1)
    - Distribution of Students by Type of Residence 1957-1977 (Box 1)
    - Food Service 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Environmental Health Department Activity Reports In Relation to Housing 1956-1963 (Box 1)
    - Housing Projects
      - Additional Student Housing 1965-1975, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Housing Regulations 1964 (Box 1)
    - Housing Reform (Box 1)
    - Housing Survey 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Michigan League 1944-1957 (Box 1)
    - Needs Assessment Coordinating Committee 1974-1976 (Box 1)
    - Office of University Housing, Staff Meetings Minutes 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - Planning 1961-1965 (Box 2)
    - Student Advisory Committee on Housing 1965-1966 (Box 2)
    - University Safety Committee 1964 (Box 2)
  - University Housing
    - Apartments-University Owned and Operated 1962-1967 (Box 2)
    - Graduate and Foreign Student Housing (Box 2)
    - Married Student Housing 1966-1968 (Box 2)
    - Medical Center Housing Studies 1961-1967 (Box 2)
    - North Campus
      - General 1967-1971 (Box 2)
      - Housing 1961-1965 (Box 2)
      - Interfaith Building 1959-1968 (Box 2)
      - North Campus Recreation Building 1973 (Box 2)
      - Northwood IV 1966-1971 (Box 2)
      - Northwood, V 1967-1971 (Box 2)
      - Outdoor Recreation 1967-1977 (Box 2)
      - Planning 1959-1977, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Residence Halls 1956-1959 (Box 3)
      - Bursley 1955-1964 (Box 3)
    - Oxford Housing 1959-1966, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Residence Halls
      - General 1969 (Box 3)
      - Administration 1939-1940, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
      - Board of Governors of Residence Halls
        - 1954-1963 1968-1971, 11 folders (Box 3)
        - Rate Study Committee 1958-1982 (Box 3)
      - Evaluation Committee of Men's Residence Halls
        - Minutes 1958-1959 (Box 3)
        - Correspondence 1957-1958 (Box 3)
      - Financing 1952-1964 (Box 3)
      - Staff Training 1956 (Box 3)
    - Residential College 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - Washtenaw Terrace Housing 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - Non-University Housing
    - General 1950-1969, 1961-1965 (Box 3)
    - Affiliated Housing 1957-1971 (Box 3)
    - Apartments
      - Privately Owned/Operated 1964-1967 (Box 3)
      - Howland, G., Developer 1963-1972 (Box 3)
    - Cooperative Housing
      - Foundation for Cooperative Housing
        - General 1964-1967 (Box 3)
        - Willow Village Apartments 1964-1966 (Box 3)
      - Inter-Cooperative Council
        - General 1956-1969 (Box 3)
        - General 1970-1972 (Box 3)
        - Department of Housing of Urban Development Grant Application Details 1968-1971 (Box 3)
        - North Campus 1957-1971 (Box 3)
        - Official Documents (Box 3)
        - Literature and Pamphlets (Box 3)
    - Low Cost/Public Oriented Housing 1965-1967 (Box 3)
    - President's Commission on Off-Campus Housing 1965 (Box 3)
    - Private Developments for UM 1964-1967 (Box 3)
    - Race Relations in Off-Campus Housing
      - General 1954-1960 (Box 4)
      - Committee on 1954-1960 (Box 4)
      - Reports 1949-1960 (Box 4)
    - Registration of Off-Campus Housing 1957-1970 (Box 4)
    - Student Advisory Committee on Housing-Subcommittee on Off-Campus Housing 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Tenant/Landlord Relations 1967-1970 (Box 4)
    - University/City Relations
      - General 1959-1970 (Box 4)
      - Community Actions on University Housing 1959-1966 (Box 4)
      - Joint Committee on Central Business District Hi-Rise Development and Parking
        - General 1964-1965 (Box 4)
        - Meeting Minutes 1964-1965 (Box 4)
- Student Activities
  The other large portion of the Ostafin collection is in the area of Student Activities. This part of the collection has little focus, but touches rather on many ephemeral issues and organizations that involve such topics as outdoor concerts in the late 1960s and student-run stores. One folder even deals with the "problem" of graffiti on the large rock at the intersection of Washtenaw and Hill Streets. The largest subseries, labeled by Ostafin as "Student Consumerism," includes the formation of a student credit union and a cooperative where both students and faculty could purchase products at a discount. The Student Activities series also has thorough documentation of the Student Government Council during its period of turmoil in the early 1970s and the resulting study by the Commission on Student Governance.
  - "Alternative" Coffee House 1969 (Box 4)
  - Blues Festivals On Campus 1969-1970 (Box 4)
  - Commission on Student Governance
    - Historical Materials 1954-1968 (Box 4)
    - Reports and Supplements 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    - Study 1973-1975 (Box 4)
    - Source Materials Consulted (from UC-Berkley) 1968 (Box 4)
  - Environmental Action for Survival Group (ENACT) 1969-1971 (Box 4)
  - Freshman Rendezvous 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - Human Relations Commission 1964 (Box 4)
  - Presidents Commission on Role of Student in Decision Making
    - Correspondence 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Meeting Minutes 1967 (Box 4)
    - Reports 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Rock at Intersection of Washtenaw and Hill 1967 (Box 4)
  - Student Attitude Studies 1961-1972 (Box 4)
  - Student Consumerism
    - Student Consumer Operations 1970 (Box 4)
    - Student Credit Union 1969-1970
      - Study Committee 1969 (Box 4)
    - Student Discount Bookstore 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - University Credit Union Non-Profit Housing Corp.
      - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes 1971 (Box 4)
      - Regular Meeting Minutes 1970 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan Cooperative 1951-1969 (Box 4)
  - Student Government Council 1967-1973, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Student Government Council 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Student Organizations-General Materials 1967-1969 (Box 5)
  - Tutorial and Cultural Relations/Volunteer Programs 1966-1971 (Box 5)
- Transportation
  The Transportation series includes fairly complete documentation of the Nite Owl Bus Service, ending with its replacement by the Dial-A-Ride Service, and documentation on student use of bicycles and motorcycles.
  - Bicycles 1958-1971 (Box 5)
  - Buses 1969-1972 (Box 5)
  - Bus Stop-Fuller Pool 1969-1970 (Box 5)
  - Motorized Cycles
    - General 1960-1969, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Safety 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - Parking
    - General 1967-1971, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Medical Center Area 1968-1971 (Box 5)
    - Parking Operations Committee 1968-1971 (Box 5)
  - Pedestrian Bridge 1968 (Box 5)
  - Reports 1965-1968 (Box 5)
- Southeast Michigan Council Of Governments
  - General 1968-1971 (Box 5)
  - Annual Reports 1969-1971 (Box 5)
  - Comprehensive Health Project 1969 (Box 5)
  - Publications and Source Materials Consulted 1965-1972 (Box 5)